Roshni Biswas

COMPUTER SCIENCE ENGINEER · BIOINFORMATICIAN

N232 242-16, NASA Ames Research Center, Moffett Blvd, Mountain View, CA 94035

□ (914)-645-0124 | 🗷 contact@roshnibiswas.tech | 回 roshni-b | 🛅 roshni079 | US Citizen

Summary.

I am presently at NASA Ames Research Center working in the Earth Science Division and the Space Biosciences Research Division as a post-bac research intern. I have a keen interest in Bioinformatics and am currently pursuing full time opportunities starting in the summer of 2019.

Work Experience _____

NASA Ames Research Center

POST-BAC RESEARCHER - BIOSPHERE & GENELAB GROUPS - DR. CHRISTOPHER POTTER & DR. HOMER FOGLE

California, USA Jan 2019 - Present

· Programming and analysis for global simulation models and MODIS satellite data sets of land cover change

• Bioinformatics support for GeneLab's sequence data processing

NASA Langley Research Center

Virginia, USA

DATA SCIENCE RESEARCH FELLOW - OCIO DATA SCIENCE TEAM - CHARLES LILES

Aug. 2018 - Dec. 2018

• Studied cloud imagery to better understand the formation and indicators of severe weather

 $\bullet \ \ \text{Implemented image processing \& deep learning models for detecting and predicting Above Anvil Cirrus Plumes \\$

GapSummit 2018 Cambridge, UK

LEADER OF TOMORROW - GLOBAL BIOTECH REVOLUTION

Feb. 2018 - April 2018

· As part of Team OneLife pitched "Blockchain medical record as a service" at Voices of Tomorrow bio-innovation contest

NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory

California, USA May 2017 - Aug. 2017

Research Fellow - Biotech & Planetary Protection Group - Dr. Kasthuri Venkateswaran & Dr. Nitin K. Singh

· Studied the effect of spaceflight on shotgun sequenced microbial samples from the International Space Station and JPL SAF

• Developed a software pipeline from open source bioinformatics tools for metagenome sequence data analysis

NIT-K Surathkal Mangalore, India

VISTING STUDENT INTERN - SPEECH & AUDIO PROCESSING - PROF. SHASHIDHAR G KOOLAGUDI

May 2016 - July 1016

• Implemented and evaluated various pitch detection algorithms using MATLAB

• Developed a tool that records, processes and assesses musical pitch

Education ____

National Institute of Technology (NIT), Rourkela

Rourkela, India

BACHELORS OF TECHNOLOGY IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

Jul. 2014 - Jun. 2018

- Graduated with a First Class Bachelors 7.0/10
- · Bachelor's Thesis: ECG signal analysis, feature extraction and classification of Arrhythmic heartbeats in human beings.

Mahadevi Birla World Academy

Kolkata

HIGH SCHOOL DIPLOMA - CENTRAL BOARD OF SECONDARY EDUCATION (CBSE)

Jul. 2012 - Jun. 2014

· High school coursework in Math, Physics, Chemistry, Biology and English

Skill-Set____

Tools/Libraries Tensorflow · Keras · OpenCV · Biopython · Bioconductor · Scikit · Git · ArcGIS

Languages English · Bengali · Hindi

Coursework .

Introductory Computer Architecture · Computer Networks · Computer Graphics · Electrical & Electronics · Digital Communication
 Intermediate Machine Learning · Discrete Mathematics · Software Engineering · Operating Systems · Data Structures & Algorithms
 MOOCs Bioinformatics Methods I (UToronto) · Using Python For Research (HarvardX) · Python for Genomic Data Science (JHU)

March 22, 2019 ROSHNI BISWAS PAGE 1

Honours & Awards

INTERNATIONAL

2018	Top 100, Leaders of Tomorrow by Global Biotech Revolution	Cambridge, UK
2017	Winner, Caltech Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship	California, USA
2014	Top 50 , 4-year Undergraduate SPDC Scholar for Persons of Indian Origin	Kolkata, India

DOMESTIC

2017	Winner, Leo Omega Club President, Lions International	Rourkela, India
2014	Winner, CBSE Problem Solving Assessment - 97.8 Percentile	Kolkata, India
2011	Winner, MBWA Extra Curricular Star of the Year - Krida Kunj	Kolkata, India

Projects

Deep Learning on Above Anvil Cirrus Plumes

NASA Langley, USA

PYTHON · OPENCV · TENSORFLOW · KERAS

Sept. 2018 - Dec. 2018

- Preprocessed IR imagery & Radar information in OpenCV, NumPy and Pandas; Labelled GOES-16 Satellite imagery using LabelMe
- · Implemented U-Net convolutional neural network model using Tensorflow and Keras to predict intense cloud plume formations

ECG Singal Anlaysis & Arrhythmia Classification

NIT Rourkela, India

PYTHON · MATLAB Aug. 2017 - April 2018

- · Used MIT-BIH Arrhythmia Dataset to perform signal analysis and detect arrhythmia in human heartbeats
- · Used Digital Signal Processing techniques to detect and segment ECG recordings and obtain features for each heartbeat
- · Implemented PCA and two ML classification models using neural networks and support vector machines

Space Metagenomic Data Analyzer Pipeline

NASA JPL, USA

PYTHON · R · TRIMMOMATIC · MEGAHIT · PROKKA · METAPHLAN2

May 2017 - July 2017

- QC, Filtering and Trimming of 420+ shotgun Illumina-sequenced metagenomic samples from ISS & JPL-SAF datasets
- Crafted a software pipeline using open source tools like MegaHit for Assembly, Prokka for Annotation and MetaPhlAn2 for Profiling
- · Generated standard compliant outputs with OTU tables & heatmap images explaining seasonal diversity and abundance profiles
- · Benchmarking and comparison of processed data with other similarly established pipelines

Pitch Recording and Assessment Tool

NITK Surathkal, India

MATLAB · Python May 2016 - July 2016

- Recorded and collected vocal audio samples from singers of varied expertise to build a dataset for the project
- Implemented a sawtooth waveform inspired pitch estimator to determine and plot fundamental frequency levels
- Objectively analyzed and assessed accuracy levels of singers in units of cents and demonstrated its correlation with expertise

Bird Migration Tracking Kolkata, India

PYTHON Dec, 2016

· Manipulated, examined and visualized tracked GPS data of 3 migrating seagulls in Python using Pandas, NumPy and Cartopy

Publications

6th International Conference on Advanced Computing, Networking, and Informatics

NIT Silchar, India

PRESENTER

April 2018

• Roshni Biswas, Y. V. Srinivasa Murthy, Shashidhar G. Koolagudi, Vishnu Swaroop G., "Objective Assessment of Pitch Accuracy in Equal-Tempered Vocal Music Using Signal Processing Approaches", Proceedings of the Sixth ICACNI, Springer, 2018

Activities & Interests

Leo Club of Rourkela - Lions International

NIT Rourkela, India

President (2017-18) | Vice President (2016-17) | Core Volunteer

June 2014 - June 2018

- Led an 80 member Community Service team under the youth wing of Lions Club International
- · Managed 20+ projects for the benefit of the under-privileged in and around the township of Rourkela
- · Conceptualised and started an annual pre-Diwali cultural program at Shanti Bhawan old-age home, Missionaries of Charity

Microsoft Campus Club CONTENT HEAD | CORE MEMBER

NIT Rourkela, India

Sep. 2014 - Apr. 2018

- Organized several coding contests, online treasure hunts, appathons and workshops
- · Head of the content team and Manager of the tech-blog